[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-four]
[第三十四集]
Laboratory and Prison
《研究室与监狱》
There are two origins of civilization in the world.
世界文明的发源地有二
The first is the scientific research laboratory.
一是科学研究室
It's a prison.
是监狱
Our youth aspire to
我们青年立志
If you leave the lab, you will go to jail.
出了研究室就要入监狱
Out of the prison into the laboratory.
出了监狱就入研究室
This is the most noble and beautiful life in life.
这才是人生最高尚优美的生活
Civilization from these two places is the true civilization.
从这两处发生的文明才是真文明
Is a civilization with life and value.
才是有生命 有价值的文明
Fellow citizens
同胞们
Now all the people in the country are up.
现在全国民众都已经起来了
Just yesterday
就在昨天
Shanghai and Tianjin have been fully implemented.
上海和天津已经全面实行了
Students strike
学生罢课
strikes of workers
工人罢工
Businessmen strike
商人罢市
Many firms in Shanghai have also posted the unveiling posts.
上海的很多商号也贴出了揭帖
Stop business with tears to save the arrested students
挥泪停业 冀救被捕学生
Don't punish the thief and swear not to open the market.
不惩国贼 誓不开市
Right now.
就在现在
Petition group organized by Beijing Federation of Students
北京学联组织的请愿团
Has arrived at the presidential palace.
已经到达了总统府
There are three requirements we put forward.
我们提出的要求有三点
The first point is to punish traitors.
第一点 惩办卖国贼
Second, Qingdao does not sign.
第二点青岛不签字
the third point
第三点
Never recognize Hu Renyuan as the president of Peking University.
绝不承认胡仁源为北大校长
And determined.
而且立志
Don't leave until you allow it.
非允后不散
good
好
Severely punish traitors
严惩卖国贼
Give me back Qingdao and my freedom.
还我青岛 还我自由
Down with traitors
打倒卖国贼
Cao Rulin Zhang Zongxiang
曹汝霖 章宗祥
The Beiyang government brutally suppressed
北洋政府残酷镇压
The atrocities of the student patriotic movement
学生爱国运动的暴行
Aroused great indignation among the people.
激起了人民群众的极大愤概
From the beginning of June
六月上旬起
Tens of thousands of teachers and students in dozens of schools in Beijing
北京数十所学校的几万师生
take to the streets
走上街头
Hold large-scale demonstrations and speeches.
举行大规模的示威和演讲活动
Workers and businessmen
工人 市民商人
And other social classes.
等各个社会阶层
Strike one after another.
纷纷举行罢工 罢市
Student solidarity movement
声援学生运动
Shanghai, Jinan, Wuhan, Guangzhou and other places
上海 天津济南武汉 广州等地
There was also a massive outbreak.
也爆发了大规模的
Strikes and strikes
罢课罢工和罢市活动
The May 4th Movement spread rapidly.
五四运动迅速蔓延
Like volcanoes.
像一座座火山
Outbreaks all over the country
在全国各地爆发
beauty
美人
Premier Qian arrives.
钱总理到
Thank you for waiting.
二位久等了
Emergency
情况紧急
The president has some unfinished business.
大总统还有些公务没有处理完
Let me come here first.
就让我先过来了
have a seat
请坐
Change of circumstances
情况有变
Both of you know the situation in Beijing.
北京的情况二位都知道
I won't say it.
我就不说了
Let's talk about Shanghai first
先说上海
Shanghai appeared this afternoon.
今天下午上海出现了
The Three Strikes of Strike
罢课 罢市的三罢
All walks of life in Shanghai are at Kalden West Hotel, Ningbo Road.
上海各界在宁波路卡尔登西饭店
Hold a joint meeting
召开联席会议
Shanghai Business School Newspaper was founded.
成立了上海商学工报
All walks of life Federation
各界联合会
And electrify the whole country.
并通电全国
Indicates that there is a traitor.
表示卖国贼存在一
Industry and commerce is the hub industry.
工商学界即毂业一
Industry and commerce are in business for a day.
工商学界即业一日
Swear not to look back
誓不反顾
Except Shanghai.
除上海以外
More than a dozen cities across the country
全国十几所城市
And Paris in Europe, Tokyo in Japan.
以及欧洲的巴黎 日本东京
There have also been large-scale
也都出现了大规模的
Protest against government activities
抗议政府活动
Today is the only day.
仅今天一天
Presidential Palace and State Council
总统府和国务院
More than 300 protest messages were received.
就收到抗议电文三百多份
unprecedented
前所未有
More importantly,
更要紧的是
The southern government is ready to move.
南方政府蠢蠢欲动
South government Xin Xin Yu dong
南方政府鑫鑫欲动
Take this opportunity to attract people's hearts.
借此收揽民心
Attack my government wantonly.
大肆攻击我政府
Even some foreign banks and trading companies.
甚至一些外国银行和商社
And asked us to control the situation as soon as possible.
也要求我们尽快控制局势
To protect the interests of foreign businessmen.
以保护外商利益
Today's education in Beijing is completely out of control.
今天北京的教育界已经完全失控
A situation that has just improved in the previous period
前一段刚刚有所起色的局面
Instantly disappear.
瞬间消失尽
Almost all schools are on the streets today.
今天几乎所有的学校都上街了
There was a workers' parade in Xindian.
长辛店出现了工人游行了
Workers, that's a big deal.
工人起来 那可非同小可
See this situation can't clean up.
眼看这个局面就无法收拾了
President Duan Shi and I just now.
刚才段师 大总统 还有我
An urgent business together.
在一起紧急商
Agree that it is imperative to control the situation.
一致认为当务之急是要控制局势
Try every means to win over the students.
想尽一切办法把学生笼络住
What's the best way to do it now?
事到如今还有什么好办法
There are ways.
办法是有的
Calling you two here is a way to do it.
叫你们二位来就是说办法的
But this way
不过这个办法
It's up to you two to implement it.
得靠你们二位去落实
Ask the Prime Minister for instructions.
请总理训示
Duan Shuai believes
段帅认为
During the negotiation with the southern government.
自前正值和南方政府谈判期间
The student disturbance.
学生闹事这个事
Has become the southern government.
已经成为南方政府
Attack a mouthful of our door.
攻击我们门的一大口实
We can't lose big because of small things.
我们不能因小失大
Make the front and rear are messed up.
闹得前方和后方都乱了手脚
We should try every means to stabilize Beijing.
我们要想尽一切办法把北京稳住
How to take the old section mainly?
怎么着 老段服软了
This is not his style.
这可不像他的风格
This is not mainly.
这不是服软
It's strategy, strategy.
这是运筹 是谋略
The nonsense novel.
行了 废话少说
What's the trick? Come on
到底有什么招 快说吧
Presidential decree
大总统令
Remove the step army from commanding Wang Huaiqing.
免去步军统领王怀庆
Guard the position of commander Duan Zhigui.
警备司令段芝贵的职务
All infantry, soldiers, etc. shall be evacuated.
所有步兵 先兵等一律撤离
Public security in Beijing
京城社会治安
It will be handed over to the Metropolitan Police Department.
交由京师警察厅负责
This makes Xu Shichang
此令 徐世昌
This is a step for students.
这是给学生一个台阶
Tell me.
我说嘛
Why am I the only one to take my life?
为什么就我一个人来领命啊
And this is only a few days.
敢情这才几天哪
Just let those two go? ：
就把那两位给开了?：
You wait.
你等等
The soldier withdrew so many students.
这军人撤了 那么多的学生
Can the police manage it?
光警察管得过来吗
Director Wu, if you have any complaints
吴总监 你要是有什么牢骚
Please send it to your master Duan Qirui.
请朝你们的大师段祺瑞发去
I'm just instructed to convey
我只是奉命传达
If you still want to come to the meeting tomorrow
如果你明天还想来开会的话
Just go and carry out the task.
就赶紧去落实任务
I'm not complaining.
我不是什么牢骚
I just want to say
我就是想说
The troops withdrew, the gendarmerie withdrew.
部队撤了 宪兵撤了
What are the police still doing there?
警察还在那儿干什么
keep the peace
维持秩序
Wait for the evacuation order
等候撤离命令
nicely
好好
Chief fu
傅总长
Instruct you to consult with the principals of each school as soon as possible.
责成你速与各校校长协商
How to deal with the aftermath of police evacuation.
警察撤离后的善后办法
The government has only one condition.
政府就一个条件
Students resume classes immediately.
学生立即复课
Just let the students go.
只要放了学生
I can coordinate.
我可以去协调
But the government must ensure that
但政府必须保证
The military police must not ask about the students again.
军警不得再过问学生的事
About school.
学校的事情
When the police get involved, it will be bad.
警察一掺和 那就要坏事
Do you think I want to take care of your shit?
你以为老子愿意管你那些破事吗
Is that your management is lax.
就是你们管理不严
Let a bunch of scholars stir up trouble among the students.
才让一帮文人动学生们闹事
If it weren't for that.
要不是这样的话
Lao tze is very comfortable.
老子舒坦得很
enough
够了
Does the noise work?
吵管用吗
Director Wu
吴总监
The dismissal order of both of them
他们二人的免职命令
It's up to you to convey it
就由你去传达
good
好
You wait.
你等等
This is your business. Why should I go?
这是你的事 干吗让我去呀
This is the instruction of Duan Shuai and the President.
这是段帅和大总统的指令
You weigh yourself.
你自己掂量
I have to I'll go.
我得我去
Director Wu, I also went to implement my work.
吴总监 我也去落实我的工作了
Decree of the President of the Republic of China
中华民国大总统令
Immediate release
即刻解除
The detention of all the arrested students
对全体被捕学生的关押
Police unconditional
警察无条件
All personnel withdraw from the temple of writing horses along the North River.
全员撤出北河沿写马神庙
The Ministry of Education is responsible for public security.
治安交由教育部负责
Xu Shichang, President of the Republic of China
中华民国大总统 徐世昌
unlocking
开锁
What's going on?
这是咋回事
Students, students
同学们同学们
You must calm down.
你们一定得冷静
Come out and talk slowly if you have something to say.
有什么话可以出来慢慢聊嘛
After collective discussion, all our students
我们全体学生经过集体讨论
Determined never to get out of prison.
致决意决不出狱
Never get out of prison
决不出狱
classmates
同学们
This is the Beijing Student Union.
这是北京学生联合会
A telegram just sent to the whole country.
刚刚向全国发出的通电电文
I was ordered to read it out.
我奉命择要宣读
The government is trifling with itself.
政府自为儿戏
Students' gratuitous quilt
学生无端被
Never disperse on its own.
决不能自行散去
The military police's reckless education undermines justice.
此次军警躁蹈教育破坏司法
Violation of human rights and contempt for humanity
侵犯人权 蔑弃人道
Why is this long privilege a country?
长此优容 何以为国
Why never get out of prison for our country?
何以为国 决不出狱
Tell me what you want.
你说你们到底要怎么样
So that the students can come out.
才能让同学们出来呢
Please be more specific.
你说得具体一点
Okay, I'll go back and ask my superiors for instructions.
我好回去向上级请示
Dismiss a traitor
罢免卖国贼
Zhang Zongxiang, Cao Rulin Lu Zongyu
曹汝霖 章宗祥阝 陆宗舆
Okay, okay, no problem
好好好 没问题
I'll ask my superiors for instructions right away.
我这就回去向上级请示啊
Yes, victory is in sight.
对 胜利在望
Hang in there. Yeah
坚持住 对
Come on, come on.
加油加油
oil; fuel charging; make a greater effort
加油
Now students' requirements are
现在学生的要求是
Must be removed
必须罢免
Cao Rulin
曹汝霖
zhang zongxiang
章宗祥
Lu Zongyu
陆宗舆
This is also their bottom line.
这也是他们的底线
Otherwise, it will be difficult to convince him.
否则的话 就很难说服他
Students push their luck.
学生得寸进尺
Explain that there must be someone behind you.
说明背后肯定有高人指点
Let's talk about it. What should we do
大家说说吧 该怎么办
I'll speak first.
我先说吧
I have received it today.
今天我已经接到
Four telegrams from President Lu from Paris.
巴黎陆总长来的四封电报
Say in Paris.
说在巴黎
Chinese delegation's residence
中国代表团的驻地
Has been surrounded by water.
已经被围得水泄不通
The local Chinese proposed
当地华人提出
The government can detain patriotic students.
政府能关押爱国学生
They can follow suit.
他们也可以效仿
China's detention envoy
关押中国专使
Don't let the students out again
再不把学生放出来
People from the delegation
代表团的人
It is likely to be regarded as a traitor.
很有可能被当成卖国贼
Be attacked by the local Chinese.
被当地华人群起而攻之啊
I studied the students' requirements carefully.
我仔细研究了学生们的要求
It's not really high.
其实不算高
After all, I didn't move out the Paris Peace Treaty.
毕竟没有把巴黎和约这条搬出
at bottom
说到底
Is nothing more than to remove Cao Zhanglu.
无非就是要罢免曹章陆
It's just exporting gas to Chinese people.
给国人出口气而已
I don't think it's because these people
我觉得不能因为这几个人
And missed the big event.
而误了大事
It's time to make up your mind.
该痛下决心了
Drag it down again
再拖下去
Students should make other demands.
学生要提出别的要求
That would be troublesome.
那可就麻烦了
I agree with Premier Qian's opinion.
我赞成钱总理的意见
I agree. I agree.
我赞成我赞成
I also agree with the Prime Minister's opinion.
我也赞成总理的意见
Director Wu, what's your opinion?
吴总监 您的意见呢
At this point.
到了这份上了
What else can I say?
我还能有什么意见
I'll just carry out your decision.
你们决策 我执行就是了
Good director Wu's attitude is very good.
好吴总监这个态度就非常好嘛
Now everyone is in agreement.
现在大家意见都是一致的
I also discussed this matter with Lao Duan.
这个事呢 我跟老段也商量过了
Now it's here again.
现在又到了
It's really time to get past this hurdle.
真的是过不去这道坎的时候了
Had to be wronged first.
只好先委屈一下
How many of them are in Cao Rulin?
曹汝霖他们几个了
So please ask Acting Chief Fu to represent me.
这样就请傅代理总长代表我
Officially to the students
正式向学生道
At the same time, the official withdrawal is released.
同时发布正式撤免
Cao Zhanglu's position order
曹章 陆的职务令
be
是
Presidential decree
大总统令
Cao Rulin Zhang Zongxiang and Lu Zong were dismissed.
曹汝霖 章宗祥 陆宗皆免职
Cao Rulin resigned at the same time.
曹汝霖同时辞去
Bank of Communications Manager Position
交通银行经理职务
Wangxiaotangshan
避往小汤山
Xu Shichang
徐世昌
Chinese academic circles Fang Luo
中国学界方罗
Chinese academic circles
中国学界万
Long live Chinese academic circles!
中国学界万岁
We won
我们胜利了
ladies and gentlemen
诸位
originally
原先
I thought Peking University was going to die this time. Really?
我以为北大这回要完蛋了 真的
But I didn't expect it to come back to life.
但是没想到 它又活过来了
So say anything.
所以说 任何事情
All need you to pass.
都需要你经过
Just stick to it one more time.
坚持再坚持的一番努力才行
I'm not as optimistic as you.
我没有你这么乐观
Now it's just a staged victory.
现在只是阶段性的胜利
Master Cai hasn't come back yet
蔡公还没有回来
The back is indispensable.
后边少不了
There must be a bigger toss behind.
后边少不了更大的折腾
And the Paris peace treaty is still to be remembered.
并且巴黎和约还待字闺中
This matter is not resolved.
这件事情不解决
Never stop.
永远都不能消停
Fortunately, there is already hope.
好在已经有希望了
Mr. Lu Xun
鲁迅先生
What spark of thought do you have?
您又有什么思想的火花
Come out and listen.
说出来听听
What have I seen this month?
这一个月 我看到了什么
The backbone of China
中国的脊梁
中富兄
仲甫兄
Enlightenment Effect of New Culture Movement
新文化运动的启蒙效应
Has already appeared.
已经显现了
East Asian lions are awakening.
东亚雄狮正在觉醒
So what's next?
那么接下来该什么
To destroy the national character
要打掉国民性中
The servility of resignation.
逆来顺受的奴性
Turn him around.
让他脱胎换骨
Then let's pursue the victory
那我们乘胜追击
Urge the government to refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty
敦促政府拒签巴黎和约
Don't give up until you reach your goal.
不达自的誓不罢休
I have a different point of view.
各位 我有点不同的观点
Modern society pays attention to their respective duties.
现代社会都讲究各司其职
We are a school.
咱们是学校
Peking University is the highest institution of higher learning in China.
是中国最高学府北京大学
We have to be 1000. We in Peking University
我们得千一点我们北京大学
What should be done
应该干的事情
We managed to get through this barrier.
好不容易我们渡过了这个关口
Now we should pay attention.
我们现在应该把注意力
How to put it as soon as possible.
放在如何尽快地
Come back to our school order.
灰复我们学校秩序上面来
The first priority is to attend class quickly.
第一要务就是赶紧上课
Mr. Shizhi, please ask patriotism and class
适之先生 请问爱国和上课
Which is Peking University's top priority?
哪一个才是北京大学的当务之急
Patriotism is not contradictory to class.
爱国和上课它不相矛盾啊
So you can save the country without class?
那你不上课 就能救国了吗
We are a school.
我们是学校
Patriotic and national salvation is a long-term solution.
爱国和救国是长久之计
Class is a daily business.
上课是日常事务
Priorities are self-evident.
轻重缓急 不辩自明了
A rare gathering in a crisis.
危局之中 难得一聚
Let's talk about our New Youth.
来说说我们《新青年》
And the Weekly Review.
和《每周评论》
What's the next step?
下一步的计划吧
I have an idea.
我有一个想法
Our New Youth has been founded for more than three years.
我们《新青年》 创办三年有余
Straight in enlightening people's thoughts.
直是在启蒙民众的思想
How about now
现在呢
People have begun to wake up.
民众已经开始觉悟了
After the awakening
那觉悟之后
what's up
干什么
I wonder if you have ever thought about this question.
不知大家可曾想过这个问题
The most realistic thing now is to boycott the Paris Peace Treaty.
现在最现实的是抵制巴黎和约
Give Qingdao back.
把青岛给要回来
You can't win if you don't take the risk.
这个冒的达不到就不能算胜利
right
对
Deqian
德潜
After boycotting the Paris Peace Treaty?
抵制了巴黎和约之后呢
If a country's
如果一个国家的
If the problem is not solved at all
根本问题没有解决的话
Similar problems will also
类似的问题还会
Come out one by one.
一个又一个地冒出来
It is also empty talk to strengthen the country and enrich the people.
强国 国富民也是一句空话
What's wrong now
现在出问题的
It's this rotten regime.
是这个腐朽的政权
Then my point is clear.
那么我的观点很明确
Beijing will fight to the end.
抗争京 就要抗争到底
I'm still a cliche
我还是老生常谈啊
I don't advocate violent revolution
我不主张暴力革命
I don't advocate talking about socialism all the time.
我也不主张成天把主义挂在嘴边
Be practical.
要讲究实际
Speaking of learning from foreign countries
说到向外国学习
My opinion is to learn from America.
我的看法还是要学习美国
Everyone, don't forget
各位同人别忘了
Our new culture movement
我们新文化运动
Our banner is science and democracy.
我们的旗帜就是科学与民主
So China needs to develop.
所以中国要发展
We must study American pressure in an all-round way.
必须全面学习美压
Deqian
德潜
Didn't you tell me the other day
前些天你不是还跟我说
Do you think Shizhi has some foreign worship?
说适之有一些崇洋媚外吗
Why don't you speak?
怎么不发言呢
Democracy means different opinions.
所谓民主 就是各己见
The so-called democracy
所谓民主
Don't hide it.
不要着藏着
I wanted to publish it.
我是想发表来着
But I really haven't organized it yet.
但是我确实还没有组织好
Shizhi
适之
Worship foreign things and never flatter me.
崇洋我有 决不献媚
Never flatter
决不献媚
Excuse me, Dr. Hu Da
请问胡大博士
These days
这些日子里
You clip a bag every day
你天天夹个包
Behind Professor Dewey's ass.
跟在杜威教授屁股后边
Like a sidekick. Isn't that flattering?
像个跟班似的 那不是献媚吗
Shizhi, I think you are particularly like a person.
适之 我觉得你特别像一个人
Who?
谁呀
Lao Tzu Liu Er beside Gu Ming
辜鸿铭身边的老子刘二
yes or no
是不是
Bannong, the reason why I say this
半农 我之所以这么说
I think we can all express our opinions.
是想我们大家可以各抒已见
However, we express our views in order to find the direction.
但是各抒已见是为了寻找方向
As for different opinions, it is familiar or not.
至于观点各异 熟是熟非
That depends on the different national conditions and times.
那是因国情和时代不同而定的
a gentleman gets along with others
君子和而不同
This harmony is what we have in common now.
这个和就是我们现在的共同点
What do you have in common?
这个共同点是什么
I think that is no matter what.
我觉得那就是无论如何
We should transform the current society.
我们要对现行的社会进行改造
It is transformation, not improvement.
是改造不再是改良
Is a revolution.
是一场革命
This is because I saw the Beiyang government.
这是因为我看到了北洋政府
After all sorts of perversions.
种种的倒行逆施之后
Come to a conclusion.
得出的一个结论
And I want to tell you.
而且我还要告诉大家
Since we have launched such a campaign
既然我们发起了这样一场运动
Then at this critical moment
那么到了这个关键时刻
We should stand up bravely.
我们就应该勇敢地站出来
Direct action
直接行动
This is also us who are awakened.
这也是我们这些觉醒者
Responsibility and responsibility in the present
在当下的责任和担当
Do you have no clothes and robes with your son?
岂无衣 与子同袍
I advance and retreat with you.
我和你共进退
I'm one of them.
我也算一个
Shouchang
守常
I have a worry.
我有一个担心
any
什么
Worried about the split of our New Youth.
担心我们 《新青年》 分裂
Now we quarrel almost as soon as we meet.
我们现在几乎一见面就要争吵
I know what you mean.
我知道你的意思
Too superstitious about Dewey's set of experimentalism.
太迷信杜威套实验主义了
Actually, he doesn't want to think about it.
其实他也不想想
China's feudal system for thousands of years
中国几千年的封建制度
How can it be changed by talking and writing?
怎么可能说说写写就改变了呢
If there is no big revolution
要是不发生一次大的革命
China can't catch up with the world trend.
中国不可能追上世界的潮流
I used to think that you two
以前我觉得你们两个
You are too radical.
你太激进
Where's Shizhi? He's too moderate.
适之呢 又太中庸了
I choose between you two.
我在你们俩之间选其中
But now I think
可是现在我想
I have more tendencies.
我有了更多的倾向了
This is bound to make Shizhi feel more isolated
这样势必会让适之觉得更孤立
Shouchang, let me remind you
守常我提醒你
Shizhi is very proud.
适之很要面子
Don't be too hard on him on some occasions.
有些场合你别太难为他
There are some things I'll tell you about him.
有些事情我说说他
He can get by.
他强过得去
You talk too much, it's hard for his face.
你说多了 他的面子过不去的
You can rest assured.
你放心吧
I didn't treat him as an outsider.
我就没把他当外人
What do you mean by tendency just now?
你刚才说的倾向是什么意思
About Marxism
关于马克思主义
A while ago, I was compiling New Youth.
前一阵子我在编 《新青年》
Next issue's manuscript
下一期的稿子
I put the long article you wrote
我把你写的那篇长文
My View of Marxism
《我的马克思主义观》
Read it again carefully.
又仔细读了一遍
At the same time, I put April 6
同时我又把四月六日
Published by the Weekly Review
《每周评论》 发表的
Chapter II of the Communist Manifesto
《共产党宣言》 的第二章
Proletarians and Communists
《无产者和共产党人》
I also read it carefully.
也仔细读了一遍
I feel a lot of feelings.
很受感触感既颇多
Be deeply touched and full of emotion
很受感触感概颇多
You said in the editor's note
你在编者按中说
Manifesto of the Communist Party
《共产党宣言》
Marx and Engels.
是马克思和恩格斯
First and foremost opinion
最先 最重大的意见
This is a great inspiration to me.
这对我有很大的启发
Shouchang, I think you are now
守常 我觉得你现在是
Chinese propaganda and belief
中国宣传和信仰
The first person of Marxism
马克思主义的第一人
So I need to ask you something.
所以有些事情我需要请教你
Ask for advice.
请教不敢当
Actually, when I was in Japan
其实在日本的时候
I've been paying attention to Marxist theory.
我就已经关注马克思主义学说了
I'm writing now.
我现在正在写
My View of Marxism
《我的马克思主义观》的
Lower part
下半部分
But I really want to know.
但是我很想知道
Your views and opinions on the first half
你对于上半部分的看法和意见
At least now I think
至少我现在觉得
Marxism is better than anarchism.
马克思主义比无政府主义
Be more reasonable
更要有理
It is more rational than Dewey's experimentalism.
比杜威的实验主义也要有理
But as to whether it is the present age or not.
但至于它是不是当今时代
The most advanced theoretical system
最先进的理论体系
It's hard to say.
这个还不好说
Because I didn't see it
为我没有看到
All Marxist works
全部的马克思主义著作
In fact, for Marxist theory
其实对于马克思主义理论
I have been paying attention to it for many years.
我已经关注了很多年
I found out when I was in Japan before.
之前我在日本的时候我就发现了
There are many people studying in Japan.
在日本有很多人都在研究
Marx's socialist theory
马克思的社会主义学说
Translated a lot of materials.
翻译了很多资料
Originally, I just read its principle.
原先我只是读它的原理
Such as historical materialism.
比如说历史唯物主义
dialectical materialism
证唯物主义
Socialism from Utopia to Science
社会主义从空想到科学
But recently
但是最近
I will combine it with the reality of China to read it.
我把它结合到中国的实际来读
The more I read, the more I feel open.
越读越觉得开穿
Brother Zhongfu, I have an idea
仲甫兄我有一个想法
If China wants to develop
中国要想求发展
We must rely on Marxist theory.
必须依靠马克思主义理论
To be our guiding ideology.
来做我们的指导思想
Besides, it's hard to find a second way.
除此之外 很难找到第二条路
Are you so sure of your conclusion?
你就这么肯定你定的这个结论
This is just my preliminary idea.
这个还只是我的初步想法
But after the May 4th Movement
但是五四运动之后
My idea is getting stronger and stronger.
我的这个想法是越来越强烈
Of course, it also needs to be demonstrated and considered.
当然 也需要经过论证和思考
So what do you think?
那你是怎么看待
Russian October Revolution
俄国的十月革命的
This question
这个问题
I published it before.
我在之前发表的
In the Comparative View of French-Russian Revolution
《法俄革命之比较观》中
I'll explain it.
就有所阐述
In general
总的来说
China's October Revolution
俄我国的十月革命
It is completely different from the British and French revolutions.
与英法革命是截然不同的
I think it is the most advanced revolution.
我认为它是最先进的革命
How do you say this?
此话怎讲
In the final analysis, the British and French revolutions of the past
以往的英法革命 归根到底
It is also a bourgeois revolution.
它还是资产阶级的革命
But the October Revolution in China was different.
但是我国的十月革命则不同
It is led by the proletariat.
它是无产阶级领导的
socialist revolution
社会主义革命
According to Marxist theory
依据马克思主义的理论
Is the inevitable result of the development of capitalism.
是资本主义发展的必然结果
In this sense.
从这个意义上来讲
It must be the most progressive revolution.
它一定是最进步的革命
I don't read many books of Marx.
马克思的书我读得不多
But I know
但是我知道
A basic viewpoint of socialist theory
社会主义学说一个基本的观点
Is the socialist revolution.
就是社会主义革命
Only after capitalism has fully developed.
只能在资本主义充分发展了之后
Talent explosion
才能爆发
But now Russia is pressing.
可是现在俄压
It is not a developed capitalist country.
并不是发达的资本主义国家呀
I didn't know this at first.
这一点我原先也不了解
But then I read Lenin's book.
但是后来我看了列宁的书之后
I just learned that/I just realized/I just found out
我才知道
Lenin has a point of view
列宁有一个观点
socialist revolution
社会主义革命
Can be in the imperialist
可以在帝国主义的
Break out in the weak link
薄弱环节当中爆发
And succeed.
并且取得成功
Look at the Russian October Revolution.
你看 俄国的十月革命
It's been almost two years now.
到现在已经快两年了
Soviet regime
苏维埃政权
Surrounded by the layers of imperialism
在帝国主义的层层包围之下
Have gained a firm foothold.
已经站稳了脚跟
This is enough to illustrate Lenin's point of view.
这个足以说明列宁的观点
Is correct.
是正确的
auv nana
那这么说
A poor and weak country like China
像中国这样积贫积弱的国家
Can also make a socialist revolution.
也能搞社会主义革命了
I'm still studying this point.
这一点我还在研究
However, the October Revolution in Russia and China
不过俄我国的十月革命
Has set an example for us.
已经为咱们做出了榜样
好寿昌
好守常
You taught me a lesson today.
你今天给我上了一课
Junman
君曼
have come back
回来啦
dad
爸
What to do
干什么去
Go to what?
千什么去
Go out with her.
陪她出去一趟
sir
先生
We'll have dinner soon.
一会儿就吃饭了啊
Add a few more dishes
多添几个菜
I'm going to invite Shouchang and Shizhi to dinner tonight.
今天晚上我要请守常和适之吃饭
good
好
scented
香
sister-in-law
嫂子
come on
来来来
I'm eating Anhui food again.
我可算是又吃着徽菜喽
Strictly speaking, this is not Anhui cuisine.
严格地说 这不是徽菜
Huizhou cuisine refers to Huizhou cuisine.
徽菜指的是徽州菜
This should be Anhui cuisine.
这应该是皖菜
Or Anqing cuisine.
或者是安庆菜
Then enjoy your meal.
那你们慢用啊
I went out to take the children to dinner.
我出去带着孩子们吃饭
Thanks, sister-in-law.
辛苦嫂子了
Don't mention it.
不辛苦
Here comes the wine, gentlemen. Hello
酒来了 先生们好
This is General Zou Yongcheng.
这是邹永成将军
Two jars of old wine brought to me by my client.
托人带给我的两坛老酒
He said it's been on for a long time.
他说放了很长时间了
We turned it on today.
今天我们把它开了
good
好
寿昌兄
守常兄
I'm willing to come to Zhongfu for dinner.
我就愿意来仲甫这儿吃饭
Look at so many good dishes.
你看这么多好菜
Old wine has also been brought out for us.
陈年老酒也给咱们拿出来了
When I was Yannian's age,
我像延年这么大的时候
It's both children.
已经是儿女双全了
Yannian has six abstinence from drinking.
延年有六戒 不喝酒
I'm not strong with him
我不强他
But I asked him to pour wine for two uncles.
但是我请他给两位叔叔倒酒
It's my respect for you both.
算是我对二位的尊重
Brother Zhongfu, what are you doing?
仲甫兄 你这是干什么呀
No, no.
不用 不用
It's nothing
没什么
The students were released.
学生释放了
Cao Rulin Zhangzongxiang Lu Zongyu
曹汝霖 章宗祥 陆宗舆
I'm glad they're all dismissed.
都免职了 我高兴
Want to drink some wine
想喝点酒
Come on, guys.
来 二位
Let me propose a toast to you first.
我先敬你们一杯啊
Did it?
干了啊
good
好
Henian
鹤年
Go to eat.
走吃饭去了
Here comes the Year of the Crane.
来吃饭了 鹤年
They are eating fish.
妈妈 他们在吃鱼
We have meat. Meat is better than fish.
咱们有肉肉 肉肉比鱼还好吃
Here, mom, get you a piece of meat.
来妈妈给你夹块肉
Why can't I go?
凭什么不让我去呀
It's too personal.
太小看人了吧
You will be eighteen next year.
你明年十八了
You can go to the table.
你就可以上桌了
The old man is also the leader of the new culture movement.
老头子还新文化运动的领袖呢
Engage in these feudal ethical codes at home.
自己在家里搞这些封建礼教
I protest
我抗议
I also protest.
我也抗议
Why don't you let me be with Yannian's brother?
为什么不让我和延年哥哥在一起
I also protest against the feudalism of the old man
我也抗议 老头子封建
Keep your voice down
小声点
Why are you so rude?
怎么这么不讲礼仪呀
Eat some meat.
快吃口肉肉
Stop protesting, go and eat meat.
别抗议了走 赶紧吃肉
Delicious
好不好吃
You all know.
你们都知道啊
I was stimulated the other day.
前两天 我受了刺激
Sort of.
可以说算是
Experienced a thoroughly remould oneself
经历了一次脱胎换骨
Brother Zhongfu, don't worry too much.
仲甫兄 别太心重了
It's all in the past
这事情都过去了
Now let's Peking University
现在咱们北大
Isn't it Peking University again
不又是北大了吗
Is Peking University the original Peking University?
北大是不是原来的北大
I don't know.
我不知道
我陈独秀
我陈独秀
It's not the original Chen Duxiu anymore.
已经不是原来的陈独秀了
This is an article I wrote yesterday.
这是我昨天写的一篇文章
Yannian
延年
Read it to two uncles.
读给二位叔叔听听
Beijing Citizen Manifesto
《北京市民宣言》
China is a nation that loves peace.
中国民族乃酷爱和平之民族
Today, though it is subjected to unbearable oppression both inside and outside.
今虽备受内外不可忍受之压迫
Renbensi purport
仍本斯旨
For the government's final minimum requirements
对于政府提出最后最低之要求
Diplomacy towards Japan
对日外交
Do not abandon the economic rights of Shandong Province.
不抛弃山东省经济上之权利
And cancel two secret agreements in four years and seven years of the Republic of China.
并取消民国四年 七年两次密约
Mianshu Cao Rulin
免徐树 曹汝霖
Lu Zongyu Zhangzongxiang Duan Zhigui
陆宗舆 章宗祥 段芝贵
Wait for six people in Wang Huaiqing.
王怀庆等六人
And expelled from Beijing.
并驱逐出京
Cancel the step army commander
取消步军统领
And the garrison commander.
及警备司令两机关
4. The Beijing Security Team will be organized by citizens.
四 北京保安队改由市民组织
5. Citizens must have
五市民须有
Absolute freedom of assembly and speech
绝对集会言论自由权
I still hope that the people can achieve this goal by peaceful means.
我市民仍希望和平方法达此目的
The government is still unwilling to make peace.
尚政府不愿和平
Completely disobey the wishes of the citizens.
不完全听从市民之希望
Soldiers can only act directly.
军人等惟有直接行动
Make a fundamental transformation.
以图根本之改造
Hereby declare
特此宣告
To the people at home and abroad for understanding.
敬求内外人士谅解斯旨
Brother Zhongfu, what does this mean?
仲甫兄 这是何意啊
This is what I'm talking about.
这就是我所说的
We should stand up bravely.
我们应该勇敢地站出来的意思
I have three points to explain.
我有三点说明啊
First, I totally agree with Shouchang.
第一 我完全同意守常的意见
Expand the student movement into
把学生运动拓展为
Social movements and mass movements
社会运动和群众运动
Make clear our requirements for the next step.
明确提出我们下一步的要求
Publicly declare
公开宣称
If the government doesn't respect public opinion
如果政府不尊重民意
We will take direct action.
我们将直接采取行动
In order to realize the fundamental transformation of society.
以图实现对社会的根本之改造
And today?
今天呢
I just want to ask the opinions of three people.
我就是想征求三位的意见
And I also want Shizhi to translate it into English.
并且也想让适之把它翻译成英文
Brother Zhongfu, that's great
仲甫兄 太好了
Mobilize the public to publish widely.
发动民众 广泛印发
Yannian, you print more
延年 你们多印一些
Give it to me after printing, and I'll distribute it myself.
印完之后给我 我亲自去散发
good
好
寿昌兄
守常兄
You are an open young tutor of Peking University professor.
你一个堂堂的北大教授青年导师
Hand out leaflets on the street.
亲自上街撒传单
What a scandal!
成何体统啊
不是史鸷
不是适之
I never put my Li Dazhao
我从来没把我李大钊
Look superior to others
看得比别人高人一等啊
Look, for the national interest
你看 为了国家利益
People can go to the streets, workers can go to the streets.
群众能上街 工人能上街
Women can go to the streets.
妇女能上街
What can't I do on the street?
我有什么不能上街的
Don't you tell people about equality and freedom every day?
你不是天天给人家讲平等自由吗
Why can't you come to me?
怎么到我这儿就不行了
Shizhi, I look at you
适之 我看你呀
Inner old morality
内心里头旧道德
It's not what it looks like.
表里不一啊
Shouchang, I've always respected you. Yes
守常 我一直敬重你是
The iron man in culture.
文化人中的铁汉子
But I really don't understand.
可是我真的不明白
You and brother Zhongfu
你 还有仲甫兄
We are all literate people.
咱们都是文化人
What are we going to talk about?
咱们要讲的是什么呢
A literate person is a scholar.
文化人就是士
Scholars pay attention to
士讲究的就是
Improve their own self-cultivation, manage home economics, good governance in the region, and finally make the national peace
修身齐家治国平天下
Have the feelings of home and country, cultivate Qi and make peace.
要有家国情怀 修齐治平
Now we have been doing self-cultivation.
现在修身 我们一直在做
Family. Is our family all together?
齐家 我们的家齐了吗
Guys, it's hard.
二位好不容易
From poverty to the present
从穷困倒到走到现在
And now?
如今呢
It's also a red rabbit in Lu Bu's horse.
也算是人中吕布 马中赤兔
But why do you have to ruin your future?
可是为什么非要自毁前程
Even at the expense of his wife and children.
甚至不惜连累妻儿老小
I really don't know what you are doing.
我真的不明自你们在干什么
Actually, that's a good question.
其实你这个问题问得好
Now let me answer you.
那现在我来回答你
I don't think people can live for themselves.
我觉得人不能为了自己而活着
You go to Changxindian
你到长辛店
Look at those dilapidated sheds.
去看看那些破败不堪的工棚
You go to the Jinpu Line to see those.
你去津浦线去看看那些
Hungry refugees in the hatchery
饿孵干里的难民
Go to Qianmen Street again.
你再去前门大街
Look at those people who beg along the street.
去看看那些沿街气讨的气
Shouldn't we order something for them?
我们难道不该为他们点什么吗
Do you expect us to be like you?
你难道要求我们像你一样
Live in a glamorous way?
光鲜亮丽地活着吗
Mr. Dazhao
大钊先生
I think what you said is too good.
我觉得您说得太好了
The country should throw caution to the wind at this point.
国家到了这个份上就应该豁出去
Give up a small family to take care of everyone.
舍小家 才能顾大家
You can't have it both ways.
鱼和熊掌不能兼得
Yannian, do you have anything to say?
延年 有你说话的份吗
Brother Zhongfu is fine.
仲甫兄 没事
Yannian can express his opinion.
延年可以发表他的意见
Sorry, Uncle Hu
对不住 胡叔叔
Shizhi
适之
I was a little harsh just now.
我刚才话有点言重了
sorry
对不住
Out of the way.
不碍事
It really doesn't matter.
真的不碍事
I know you are an open-minded person.
我知道你是个坦荡之人
Sit down, gentlemen.
二位 坐下
Sit down, both of you
二位全 坐下
You all know I like to argue.
你们都知道 我喜欢争论
Only by arguing can the truth come out.
争论才能出真理嘛
Let's raise our glasses.
来我们举杯
come
来
Shizhi
适之
It's not you, it's you.
不是 你这个人就是这样
You don't have to hide.
你不用藏着着
Tell me what you think.
你有什么想法你就说
I'm not hiding it.
我没有藏着着呀
I think
我认为
Brother Zhongfu wants to make this civic declaration.
仲甫兄要搞的这个市民宣言
It's unnecessary.
是多此一举
Besides, Mr Dewey has just arrived in China.
况且现在杜威先生刚刚来到中国
Just entered Beijing.
刚刚进入北京
So every day I'm busy arranging some for him.
所以每天我要忙着给他张罗一些
About the speech.
演讲的事情
I need to talk to the Ministry of Education about all these things.
这些事情我都需要去和教育部
And some government departments.
还有一些政府部门打交道
Please come forward and arrange it in person.
请他们出面亲自来安排
I don't want to make these relationships too rigid.
我不想把这些关系搞得太僵硬了
Mobilize the citizens for democracy. I agree.
发动市民争民主 我同意
I also agree with the five points mentioned.
所提这五条我也同意
Especially the fifth one.
特别是这第五条
But what it says here
但是这上面所说的
I wait for students, businessmen, laborers and soldiers.
我等学生 商人 劳工 军人等
Only direct action.
惟有直接行动
It's not necessary to be too tough.
过于强硬 没有必要吧
Shizhi, why is this unnecessary?
适之 这怎么叫没有必要呢
This sentence is the most important, it can't live without it.
这句话最重要 它不能没有
Shizhi, let me explain.
适之 你听我解释啊
From the New Cultural Movement to the May 4th Movement
从新文化运动到五四运动
This is a causal relationship.
这是个因果关系
The former is ideological enlightenment.
前者是思想启蒙
The latter is put into action.
后者是付诸行动
Whether you like it or not
不管你乐不乐意
These are you and me over the years.
这些都是你我这些年
The result of direct promotion
直接推动的结果
Now the national consciousness
现在 国民觉悟
Put it into action.
付诸行动了
This is a leap.
这是一次飞跃
As the initiator, we can't stop it.
我们作为首倡者 不能阻拦
You can't stop it.
你也阻拦不了
sun yat-sen
孙中山先生说
The world tide is mighty.
世界潮流 浩浩荡荡
If you follow the rules, you will prosper; if you follow the rules, you will die.
顺之则昌 逆之则亡
We should be promoters.
我们要做促进派
Can't be a capitulator.
不能做投降派
To save China
要想救中国
Only let the people face it directly
只有让民众直接面对
There is no other way
别无他途
I'm thinking.
我是考虑到
There are many people with your thoughts.
像有你这种想法的人有很多
Therefore, my wording is mild.
所以我措辞还比较缓和
I hope you can understand
希望你能理解
I noticed that.
这点我注意到了
Shizhi May 4th Movement to this day
适之 五四运动到今天
It's been over a month.
已经有一个多月了
People have paid a lot.
民众已经付出很多了
We can't withdraw the fire, we can only add firewood.
我们不能撤火 我们只能添柴
Don't work harder, Beiyang government
不加把劲 北洋政府
It's likely to take the risk of the world. No
很可能会冒天下之大不
Go one's own way
一意孤行地
Sign the Paris peace treaty.
在那个巴黎和约上签字
until this moment
到那个时候
Not only have we lost all our efforts.
我们不但前功尽弃
The country is in danger.
国家也难保了
Japanese wolf ambition
日本人的狼子野心
You can understand it if you are a person.
是个人就看得明白
When the country is in danger
在国家危亡之际
In the face of national interests
在国家利益面前
We can't leave Germany alone.
我们不能离心离德
Brother Zhongfu, don't worry
仲甫兄 你放心
I won't hold you back.
我不会拖你们的后腿的
Although now
尽管现在
We have some differences in our thoughts.
我们在思想上有些出入
But patriotism saves the nation.
但是爱国救国
Strive for democracy and development
争民主求发展
We must agree in the general direction.
在大方向上我们一定是一致的
I agree with the declaration you drafted.
我同意你起草的这个宣言
I would also like to translate it into English.
我也愿意把它翻译成英文
But you two distinguished professors of Peking University
不过你们两位堂堂的北大教授
I strongly disagree with handing out leaflets.
出去撒传单我坚决不同意
As for throwing leaflets on the street.
至于上街撒传单再说
That's equivalent to the flesh ammonium tiger.
那相当于肉身铵虎
come
来
One thousand drinks for three of us.
我们三个千一杯
Today, we're going to put these two jars of old wine
今天我们要把这两坛子老酒
Drink up
都喝光
According to the informant
据线人报
The mimeograph society at No.18 Dagou
大沟头十八号的油印社
It is also a unique printing point.
也是独秀的一个印刷点
Sometimes some leaflets that are not suitable for printing in Peking University.
有时候一些不宜在北大印的传单
Especially some made by Li Dazhao.
特别是李大钊搞的一些
A long article introducing Marxism
介绍马克思主义的长文
Most of them are printed here
多数在这里印刷
Not many.
数量不多
Looks like it's not for distribution.
看来不是为了散发
It's supposed to be for reading.
应该是供传看的
What do you think?
你们是怎么想的
It is necessary to strengthen supervision of those behind the scenes.
要对幕后的人加强监管
Prevent them from making moves.
防止他们出手
Divisional teams
各区署队
Secret check according to the address opened.
按照所开地址秘密检查
The key point is No.18 Dagoutou
重点是大沟头十八号
check
查
be
是
come
来
Mind the Step
小心台阶
Leg lift
抬腿
under
底下
nicely
好好
be careful
小心
You said you really drank so much.
你说你们真是的 喝这么多
Shizhi also drinks so much.
适之也喝这么多
This Dongxiu just gave birth.
这冬秀刚生完孩子
What if he goes back and throws up and goes crazy?
一会他回去吐了发疯了怎么办
Sister-in-law doesn't blame brother Zhongfu for this.
嫂子 这事不怨仲甫兄
I
我
The main thing is that I'm not very talkative.
主要是我不太会说话
It made Shizhi feel bad.
让适之难受了
He drank too much.
他就喝多了
Shouchang, I didn't drink too much
守常我没喝多
nicely
好好
I haven't had enough.
我还没喝够呢
Brother Zhongfu, please stay.
仲甫兄你们留步吧
Yannian and I will take him back.
我跟延年送他回去
good
好
Who will you send?
你送谁
Send you.
送你啊
so-and-so
谁谁
Don't send me.
都别送我
I'm not drunk.
我没醉
I said I didn't drink too much.
我者说了我没喝多
I go
我自己走
good
好
Walk by yourself
自己走
Let him go alone.
让他自己走
Shizhi
适之
etc
等等
I'm not drunk.
我没醉
I
我
Not drunk
没醉
I didn't.
我没
etc
等等
I'm really not drunk.
我 我真的没醉
You wait.
你等等
Shizhi
适之
Kanke, watch your step ahead.
前路坎珂 小心脚下
Zhongfu
仲甫
Shouchang
守常
Qianlu Kanke Let's
前路坎珂 咱们
Watch your step.
小心脚下
I'm leaving
我走了
You slow down.
你慢点
I'm not drunk with my shoes.
我的鞋 我没醉
I'll go by myself, sister-in-law
我自己走 嫂子
I
我
寿昌你
守常 你
Take care of Zhongfu
你照顾一下仲甫啊
Okay, you can rest assured.
好你放心吧
I'm not drunk, sister-in-law
我没醉 嫂子
You haven't drunk for a while and fell into the mud.
还没醉一会儿掉泥里头了你
Yannian, screw your dad.
延年 管你爸去
Watch the road
看着路
My shoes
我的鞋
Brother Zhongfu, I will turn over what you told me at night.
仲甫兄 你交代的事我晚上就翻
I won't keep you.
不耽误你
Yannian, you help him over.
延年 你把他扶过去点
Slow down, slow down.
慢点 慢点
come on
来来来
中富兄
仲甫兄
That thing
那东西
It should not be printed in the red chamber.
不宜在红楼印
Too ostentatious
太招摇
I see
我知道
I'll go to Dagou for printing tomorrow.
明天我去大沟头印
Leave this to me.
这事交给我吧
It's all from me.
发都由我来
It's not convenient for you to come forward
你不方便出面
Shouchang, I have made up my mind.
守常 我是下了决心了
You go to print like this
这样 你去印
Let's meet at Dagoutou tomorrow noon.
明日中午我们大沟头碰面
We're half each other.
咱俩一人一半
Go at night.
晚上去撒
You know what?
这样吧
Give me the manuscript first.
你先把稿子给我
About handing out flyers tomorrow.
明天撒传单的事
Don't let Yannian know
别让延年知道
Don't involve Yannian, either.
也别奉扯上延年
I don't want him involved.
我不想让他掺和进来